[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software SC radio has an opening for a
volunteer host to produce five episodes
per year to apply please follow the
instructions on our website at se-
radio.net cont
this is Sam tagert for SE radio I'm here
today with Cody everon to talk about
navigating regulated environments Cody
is a co-founder and CTO of Med Plum a
developer platform that provides tools
for security interoperability and
compliance in the healthcare sector Cody
began his career as a software
development engineer at Microsoft over
15 years ago and has since held various
roles in a variety of healthcare related
tech companies such as director of
engineering CEO and CEO welcome thanks
Sam happy to be here yeah so we're going
to talk about regulated Industries why
don't we start by just defining what we
mean by regulated Industries yeah it's a
great question I think it applies in
quite a few different places typically
people think of it as I mean everywhere
has regulations but when we think of
excessively regulated or high regulation
it's places like health care or Finance
or security where there's quite a few
additional layers of requirements to
make sure that you're meeting legal
requirements ethical requirements you're
protecting user rights user data user
safety and they're all over the place
and I think there's regulation
everywhere but maybe there's a spectrum
of some that are more or less regulated
yeah I was going to say a lot around
Financial stuff I imagine and personal
information and those type of things as
well absolutely yep certainly compared
to something like video games where you
know it's it's fun but when you're
talking about financial data or
Healthcare data I think people have a
higher expectation of reliability and
security yeah so who makes these Reg
like where do they come from that's a
great question it's typically a
government or an industry standards body
so in our case we're primarily in
healthcare it's usually originating from
Healthcare government bodies like HHS
Health and Human Services and they
provide a whole bunch of different
regulations most famously Hippa but
there's quite a long list there's also
quite a few industry standard bodies and
customers will often dictate those so
where the government might not fully
regulate something the market ends up
filling those as well is that like the
what is it pcis or the credit card
Finance yeah pcis like sock 2 is a big
one to make sure that you have adequate
data and security controls those are
typically driven by the market and what
are these regulations generally trying
to prevent I think there's a lot of it
that's you might hear about it and think
well that's kind of common sense right
like that the user's data is being
adequately protected that you have
sufficient controls to make sure that
like a rogue software engineer can't go
and steal data or do something ious that
it's protecting the users data
protecting the users safety on the
ethical side not that you can truly
regulate ethics but trying to codify
those into systems so that the software
is going to be reliable I mean I think
the crowd strike attack from was that
last week or two weeks ago was a notable
one of you know there was a lot of
damage that was Financial damage human
time wasted those regulations are often
put in place to try to protect against
incidents like that so how do
regulations vary over G geography and
what challenges have you run into with
that that's a great question regulations
are often quite different CrossCountry
boundaries the US Health Care system is
perhaps one of the largest Health Care
Systems it has its own idiosyncratic
regulations but there are quite a few
that go across International boundaries
as well for example sometimes there's
data format requirements and there's
regulations to try to improve
interoperability across those different
systems there is a push from the isos so
there are many of these ISO standards
now which are an attempt to try to
standardize and regulate as an
international standards body there's a
long long list of the ISO standards and
the US government is oftentimes steering
into those to align with like the rest
of the world so in the US we have the
federal government we also have state
governments do you notice any
differences between states that apply to
health care in particular since that's
your area there's definitely a lot of
state level requirements for the
practice of medicine so on doctors and
nurses and the variety of different
roles as a healthcare provider with
regards to healthcare technology the
rules are typically pretty similar one
thing that's interesting for healthcare
is there's the notion of an hi and
health information exchange which is
allows Regional hospitals to share data
with each other and you can kind of
think of those like a homeowners
association where they have all their
special rules that Define who can share
what data between different hospitals
and that's very very Regional but not
typically so much from the state at that
point it's typically going to be the
market driving those rules so have you
ever encountered regulations that are at
odds with each other and what do you do
in those situations that's a great
question in healthcare a good example of
this would be the US government a lot of
governments are now pushing the right to
be forgotten for patients to be able to
request their data to be deleted and
purged and which is a very sensible
consumer protection but then on if you
think about the medical legal liability
requirements where you have to retain
many of your records for S years and up
to 18 years in some cases so now you
have to retain records for legal
purposes and those two are totally at
odds with each other in practice those
don't come into conflict very often and
when they do that's when you call up
your lawyers and try to figure out how
you're going to handle that putting data
into vaults or escrow or trying to semi
anonymize data it's often a long and
complicated process but when the
conflicts come you typically get the
lawyers involved yeah as G say I would
imagine if you told your doctor you were
allergic to something you would probably
want him to remember that yes or if you
have a surgical operation and the
statute of limitations on how like the
process of suing for a complication can
be available for up to seven years but
if you want to have your data deleted
like how do you reconcile those things
so have you noticed similarities across
different Industries and what are some
of the common requirements yeah
absolutely and that's where so sock 2 is
a big one that's very crosscutting and
there's a lot of common sense things in
there sometimes it's difficult to
operationalize but it can be common
sense of making sure you have like
you're using SSL or TLS on all of your
Cloud endpoints and that you have
adequate data protections so those are
cross cutting and then certainly if
you're going to do any work with the
federal government then you have
something like fed ramp which is kind of
the gold standard of all regulations and
it's going to make sure that you're
running continuous security training you
have all your security audits your pen
tests on a regular basis you have to
demonstrate that you can respond very
quickly to security vulnerabilities or
changing security requirements and that
not industry specific at all anytime you
want to work with a federal agency you
have to make sure that you're conforming
with those requirements and now the
market has adopted those rules in some
cases as well so even if you're not
working with the federal government you
may need to say okay yes we're feder
ramp compliant okay how do these
regulations affect developers how do
they translate down to the code level
absolutely that's a great question and I
think that there's the surface level
knee-jerk reaction that most software
Engineers have which is gross I don't
want to deal with that right it's going
to be a long slog a lot of complicated
boring requirements I think that there's
a more positive interpretation maybe
this is my personal bias I actually
personally kind of like them because I
view them as just a very clear and
explicit bright line set of constraints
and software engineering often is about
working with constraints and using
constraints to Define project specs and
specs translating into feature
requirements and feature requirements
translating into code so for example our
organization we've made it one of our
core competencies of taking those rules
and regulations and translating into
unit tests translating into integration
tests so that every time we run our cicd
pipelines we're going to know very
clearly like this change break or
violate one of those compliance and
certification programs do you have a
specific example yes so everything
inside of our sock 2 that we can
translate into cicd checks we have a lot
of those would be mostly on data privacy
and protections like things like access
controls I think most systems inevitably
have a gazillion checks for permissions
and access controls making sure that
various groups can only access the data
that they're supposed to have access to
etc etc so there's things like third
party tools here as well so things like
we use sonar Cube for a lot of our
automated testing which will run through
a huge battery of security tests Mozilla
Observatory that's a great one for all
of the like HTTP and TLS and SSL
endpoints all of those tools are great
and we try to run them in an automated
fashion as much as possible so that
brings me to another question so when
things go wrong and somehow one of these
regulations gets violated where does the
liability typically lie does it ever lie
directly with the developers or is it
more of a company level thing or how
does that work yes it can lie with the
developers and so that makes us very
keenly aware it makes you sit up
straight and pay attention I think that
there's typically like a remediation
period and then there's an ongoing
investigation to figure out how did this
go wrong why did it go wrong and they do
try to look at intent and with what
level of you know seriousness were you
operating in if it's gross negligence
then that's where the really big
penalties and the big fines come out if
it's something that was like a very deep
and complicated Edge case that then
there's maybe a little bit more leniency
in those situations but typically a
government agency will roll up their
sleeves dig into what happened and try
to make that type of assessment before
levying fines and penalties so something
that just popped into my head is how do
you balance and maybe this isn't a
question for you but just curious if
you've seen it done balancing the desire
for people to actually report incidents
so that everybody can learn from them
versus if you smack people really hard
they're going to be reluctant to
disclose some of those incidents yeah
the first thing that comes to mind there
is like the security industry at large
and the culture that exist there of
things like bug bounties and I think
that that's been very fascinating to
watch over the last 10 or 20 years how
that's evolved because I think that for
a long time software developers and
software
organizations generally wanted to swap
those people away if someone came to you
and said hey I think I found a
vulnerability the first thing you want
to do is try and shut them up and make
them go away and what I think the
industry has found over time is that you
should welcome those you should invite
those people and make sure that you have
a responsible disclosure program so that
the issue can get fixed in a timely
fashion so I think that that has evolved
nicely and has done very very well with
regards to like how government agencies
enforce this it's perhaps a little bit
less mature because it happens less
frequently it is done on a somewhat
case-by case basis for sure certainly in
the cases of the kind of gross
negligence there have been cases in the
past where there's just like an open FTP
server accessible on the internet where
you can download lots of patients data
and it was just security through
obscurity there was you if you knew the
IP address you could just log in and
grab a bunch of data that's pretty bad
and I don't think they hold back at all
when it comes to penalties and fees and
fines but if it's you know you were
using now dated encryption library and
like an old version of SSL that had some
longtail vulnerability I think that
they're generally pretty forgiving and
understanding in those situations great
so what are some of the challenges that
you've seen complying with
regulations I think there's just often
like it feels like a large body of work
associated with it right you sometimes
you get the packet and so okay we're
going to start up a new compliance
program for a new certification or we
have a new customer that's based in
Europe and now we need to figure out how
to make sure that we're meeting all the
requirements for the EU or for
Switzerland or whatever so you typically
there's a variety of vendors that you're
going to work with who may or may not
have automated tools if you're lucky
there's a high degree of overlap with
some of your existing compliance
programs if you're unlucky that could be
hundreds of pages of very technical and
dry legal documentation that you just
need to start going through and
translating into product and feature
requirements and process requirements
and that's just it's a form of work but
it's also that's part of the value
proposition of the industry too so it's
definitely a challenge I'd say it's if
you think about the umbrella of software
engineering we often think about
challenges as being hard technical
problems but more often than not I think
software engineering is working with
process problems and cross functional
coordination problems and compliance
certification is just another layer of
that it's another kind of role another
party in the room with your compliance
and security folks and just making sure
that all of those requirements are
represented okay yeah my next question
that popped into my head was the process
for taking these regulations and
figuring out like how we have to
implement them in the software how does
that work is that mostly the security
people or the compliance people making
those decisions or they doing it with
the developers are they just pushing it
up developers being like you got to
comply with this how does that work yeah
that's great question it's a little bit
of all the above there are some that are
just Global you just have to do it right
in our case in healthcare Hippa it's
just kind of like it's table stakes and
so you have to pretty much have that as
part of your process on day one I think
sock 2 is kind of becoming at that level
is it becoming a table Stakes
certification that you just pretty much
have to start it and do it in other
cases it might be at the time that
you're evaluating some new like business
opportunity a new customer a new sale or
moving into a new market and then it's
perhaps a little bit more of a cost
benefit analysis you know the lawyers
and the compliance team will be in the
room and part of that conversation you
can boil that down to a dollars and
cents pros and cons analysis then
there's the you know as these
regulations are not static they change
over time and new rules can get added
and so typically every year or so the
rules may change and you have to
recertify or go through an audit again
that always happens as well and in that
case it just depends sometimes it is
long process of sitting down translating
requirements there's some I will
definitely give a shout out to various
US government agencies that have now
started publishing automated testing
tools so for example Health and Human
Services has started publishing some of
their tools so you can actually take
your public htb API endpoints and plug
it into some of their automated tooling
and they'll run their battery of tests
against your publicly accessible
endpoints and that's a fantastic way to
do it it takes a lot of the guesswork
out of it it takes a lot of the legal
cost of pouring through through boring
documentation but that's still
relatively rare I think it's a great
model for the future but whenever it
happens it's fantastic yeah one question
I had was kind of how you maintain it
over time do the agencies publish when
they change regulations is it your
responsibility to constantly stay up on
that how does that work they do publish
new versions and technically yes it is
our responsibility to stay on top of all
that and as we recertify that's on us
most of the certification programs there
is like an audit step and so there's
approved third party Auditors that will
go through your product and all of your
documentation all your policies to make
sure that you're up to dat and you're in
compliance in practice most
organizations will use a security tool
or provider so for example vanta is the
big player in this space there's quite a
few other competitors as well who they
provide automated tooling that will you
know scan your environments like actual
agents that will run inside your Cloud
environment or agents that will run on
your servers inside your private
networks to ensure that this whole
battery of checks is actually being met
then they'll turn around and produce a
lot of that documentation for you it
doesn't produce 100% maybe 80 or 90% so
it does a lot of the work but ultimately
as a provider our organization is still
responsible it's still our butt on the
line to work with the Auditors and make
sure that all of their requirements are
satisfied so you mentioned cost earlier
do you have any idea how much cost the
regulations add and then as an add-on to
that question have you ever run into
situation where you've had to cancel a
project due to cost or do you usually
figure out a way to pass that onto the
customer how does that work okay one at
a time an approximation of cost is kind
of tricky and I think that it does
change depending on the size of your
organization as well but you know it's
easily measured in the cost of like
full-time employees so it's a
non-trivial cost for sure but it's you
know I guess part of the cost of doings
business for working in the space with
regards to how customers like the
easiest maybe example would be you're
going to move into a new market and in
particular going into Europe or like
Australia these are countries that often
have very strict data sovereignty
requirements and they're domestic
government agencies will have their own
requirements and then yes at that point
it usually is a costing exercise to go
through the requirements and try to make
a guesstimate on like both time money
engineering effort what's it going to
take sometimes you can pass that on to
the customer that's usually part of the
overall like Enterprise deal
negotiations and it's kind of a mixed
bag where that's all going to net out I
think most organizations you know that
becomes more of like a strategy question
than a technical question of like is
this Market is this geography important
to us and do we think it's worthwhile
moving into it if it is you go for it
okay so bringing things back to
developers how can developers be quote
agile for whatever that means anymore
and maintain velocity in regulate
environments yeah you have any specific
examples of that I think it comes back
to that idea of constraints and there is
this popular perception that compliance
certification and regulations is like
slow and I would maybe try to reframe
that just a little bit which is it can
be slower to start but I personally
believe you know after years of doing
this that going through that initial
pain of you know building out all those
unit tests all those integration tests
to take all those regulations and
translate that into product requirements
and translate that into infrastructure
it's technical it's going to run on
every build or every deployment I
actually find that if you're willing to
kind of pinch your nose and power
through on that that you end up in a
place where you actually have very very
high velocity because you now have all
these systems in place in an automated
fashion and you can ship with confidence
you can build add new features with
confidence you can refactor with
confidence but over time that is like
the truest form of velocity that you can
you know as you grow in scale you can
ship faster and faster and that just
gets back and if that there's an element
of just software engineering best
practices there of making sure that you
have your product requirements
represented with some form of automated
testing so that it doesn't have to be a
big manual effort it doesn't have to be
a big legal or compliance push that your
tools and your processes and your
systems are the ones that are really
keeping you accountable over time so you
mentioned
requirements what happens when the
requirements change and along those
lines do you separate Out product
requirements from compliance
requirements we use a variety of
techniques to try to stay organized
within that realm there's a very high
degree of overlap between those two as
you can imagine we use a combination of
a code organization putting various
compliance packages into just different
folders or different packages or modules
with our documentation and issue
tracking we use various like sub
projects or tags to represent all the
different compliance and verification
programs some the programs are are more
specific on this point than others for
example I've gone through FDA medical
device before that's a whole separate
process for clearing a medical device
and the FDA has a set of requirements
regarding they call it the traceability
Matrix so for any given you know feature
then you have to go and make sure that
you've identified and iterated all the
potential risks and for every one of
those single risks you need to make sure
that you've iterated through all the
different tests that you can use to try
to mitigate those risks and you have to
have a full tagging system that connects
every single one of those Concepts and
that has to be represented both in your
documentation but also in your processes
and in your code so our current product
is not FDA regulated but we've tried to
take a lot of those same Concepts and
apply it to our processes just because
once you get over the initial pump of of
doing all that work then you end up in a
good place where you have all that
infrastructure those those systems in
place but you can really crank through
the documentation and you can add new
programs and new certifications
relatively quickly it's interesting
mentioned traceability matrices because
that was going to be my next question
because we used to do those in the
nuclear industry a lot yes it is
daunting when you first see that right I
mean I I remember as I was first
entering Healthcare and first
encountering FDA and you kind of get
those packets of Regulation it does kind
of hit you in the face with whoa this is
going to be a lot of work but I I do
believe that if you can power through on
it it creates a lot of value and both
like Financial value for your
organization but just technical value in
terms of really maturing and leveling up
processes and systems yeah I think you
buildt a lot of tooling around that
pretty quickly because otherwise I I
think you would be hting life yes yes
you would need a lot of manual effort to
go through and try to reverse engineer
all that documentation and all those
requirements so what role does uh cicd
play in all of this we're big Believers
in cicd and and we have have embraced
that since day one so that on every
commit it'll go through the battery of
tests and if it satisfies everything it
rolls straight out to production and so
we deploy dozens of times per day that
is per it's not required anywhere and I
still think that it's probably not quite
the norm especially in in healthcare
just yet it's changing I personally
believe that cicd is a huge role to play
If you're willing to go through that
pain of you know translating the all
those requirements into the test and
that is work for sure and I don't think
there's any shortcuts there but it's
Turing in a good direction so do you
find you're generally able to make those
tests reusable across projects or are
they specific to a project certain tests
yes like anything where it's like oh
this is an HTP end point therefore it
has to meet all these big basic security
requirements and that generalizes really
nicely across the board when you get
into the more nuanced and like feature
specific then maybe not some of the data
requirements with regards to like
mandating requiring certain like data
formats so if like in our world in
healthcare things like hl7 and fire are
are very common as standard and required
data formats and data represent
presentations that those become all of
our schema validation and object
validation data type validation all that
is is very deeply ingrained in all of
our tests and so that applies across the
board so that's another good one good so
I'm personally a big fan of tester
invelopment in this idea of like
emerging or just in time design do you
find that the regulations force you to
do more design up front or are you able
to kind of design as you go or how does
that work so our team includes mostly
experienced industry veterans and I
think think that after being in the
space you develop some scar tissue and
you develop a strong desire to do some
of that work upfront to make sure that
your systems are going to support it you
it's like you're laying the foundation
of the house you want to make sure that
you're you know building on a rock solid
foundation the kind of evolving nature
of requirements or oh shoot we need to
add a garage to the side of the house
and we didn't have a foundation didn't
there was no concrete there like that
never feels great and it feels like you
have to do this Mad Dash and lots of
like organiz ational refactoring and
code refactoring and project refactoring
so that doesn't feel as good I think
that when we do embrace it and we know
our list of requirements upfront and we
can plan accordingly to have everything
properly organized definitely gives a
better sense of security and
sustainability as you think about the
future and ongoing growth of the project
yeah that just brought up an interesting
thought in my head for some reason and
that is if you have multiple groups
working on different parts of a project
how do you coordinate between them and
how do you make sure that they're all
all staying in compliance and that like
the workflow between the groups stays in
compliance I would think that would be a
challenge and I think that one of the
hardest parts of any software system to
test in an automated fashion is like
your contract testing your boundary
testing right and that's not even so
much a unique challenge to regulated
environments that's just a hard software
engineering challenge and I I think what
that comes down to is making sure that
your tests are represented at multiple
different layers so it's not just unit
test for each of the kind of component
modules but also as you're deploying to
like Canary environments and staging
environments and whatnot that you're
running integration tests that properly
Test the full end to end requirements or
user stories or what have you that it
has to be kind of tested at that
holistic level as well so what mix would
you say are unit tests versus end to-end
tests in general good question I
personally don't love that distinction
because I think that there's kind of a
blurry area in the middle there too for
things like data formats or like basic
algorithms that conform nicely to a unit
test that's always better right you're
closer to the code that's going to run
faster the development and test cycle is
just a tighter Loop and you can just
move so much faster when you get to the
notion of like very complex systems and
you have like microservices or just you
know any degree of multiple services
that are interacting with each other now
you basically force yourself into a
world of requiring those like
integration tests and end to end tests
I'd say if I were to just put some like
simplified numbers on it we're probably
not too far off from a 50-50 blend of
lots of small unit tests and then lots
of integration tests that and those
integration tests have to go all the way
from you know making sure that you're
testing against a proper database and a
and a a reddis cluster and you know
multiple servers and multiple database
instances to make sure that you know the
full complexity of the system is being
represented there yeah so do you find
then you don't do a lot of mocking or do
you do a lot of mocking and test stubs
and things like that we try to avoid
mocking as much as possible just as a
general principle the key points where
you know if you're using various like
thirdparty cloud services for sending
emails or for storing objects in like an
an awss 3 or something like that we mock
those endpoints but for everything else
we have a tendency to avoid mocking as
much as possible I think perhaps one of
the more controversial ones would be
like whether you mock out your database
calls and so most of our serers side
application that would ever result in
something running a a seq query against
a postgress database we have a strong
preference for making sure that those
are actually hitting postgress when as
we run our test Suites I personally
believe that trying to mock database
queries is for us at least it's it's
it's not a good fit and we we get a lot
more confidence when it's actually
touching the database and where that has
proven to be very valuable is as our
project grows in age and you start to go
through various versions of postest or
various versions of reddis and you okay
the postest 12 to 14 upgrade uncovers
whole bunch of you know subtle changes
in various syntactic differences that
would not have happened if we had been
mocking out those various you know
infrastructure components so integration
testing at that level I I'm a huge fan
of good so how does regulation effect
maintaining Legacy code there's a good
question there and I think that there's
maybe it's a case where sometimes the
regulation can be at odds what the
market wants and certainly what
customers want because sometimes the
regular is going to push you to upgrade
to newer features newer security
protocols newer encryption protocols etc
etc and you know from a software
engineering perspective I think that's
great we should you know keep moving the
line forward but often times there for a
variety of reasons maybe some customers
a partner does not want to upgrade and
so now you have a bit of a pickle there
of how far back should you maintain
backwards support Legacy support and
that's kind of a case-by casee basis I
think that there are typically there's
outs for like grandfathering things in I
think in healthcare one of the funniest
examples is faxing typically we think of
faxing is crazy outdated Legacy
technology but it's still very widely
used in healthcare as an
interoperability format primarily
because it's grandfathered in and I
personally think it's hilarious when you
read through these various like
healthcare requirements and oh mandating
this form of encryption and this
security protocol da da and then you get
to the section on faxing and it's like
try make sure the fax machine is in the
back room so people can't see the pages
as they're getting printed out and so
that's a you know pretty star position
but I think it's just acknowledging the
truth that sometimes Legacy systems are
important and you have to maintain them
just as a pragmatic matter yes so how do
you balance the security versus
stability because I would think that and
I think maybe you hinted on this a
little bit like security says that you
should update your things to patch the
latest vulnerabilities but then that has
to affect stability and then in addition
to that
I assume there's some cost to revalidate
stuff after you change it yes absolutely
and is a very common pattern for us we
as we're introducing a new feature you
know we believe strongly in things like
feature flags and deploying to
production but in a disabled fashion or
running multiple implementations in
parallel you know you have your existing
implementation which is providing the
customers with whatever Services you're
providing but you're running your next
version in parallel as a bit of like an
internal smoke test or an internal
Canary and comparing the results of
here's what the old version did here's
what the new version did are they
producing the same results and if yes
great if no okay let's set off some
alarm bells and you know either that
comes back to our team and we need to
check our assumptions and see like hey
is this breaking something or if it's
something about how the client was
interacting with the service then we
might need to engage them in a
conversation and start a migration
process so obviously it's it's a know
bad thing to you know test in production
and have your customers do your testing
for you but I think that when you deploy
multiple versions and and have one in a
kind of Shadow enabled fashion that you
can quotequote let your customers test
for you but you're doing it in like a
log only fashion until you've achieved
some level of confidence that okay we
know that all of our existing customers
and all of our current usage is we can
flip this switch and high confidence
that it's going to work as expected yeah
I've heard of that before I believe I've
seen that referred to as the Strangler
fig pattern Strang I'm not familiar with
that ter basically yeah I think there's
these fig trees that grow up and they
grow around an existing tree and then
eventually the existing tree dies and
you just end up with this hollow shell I
love it yes it's a great metaphor and it
kind of perfectly describes it you also
mentioned logging can you talk about
some of the challenges with logging I
mean one of the big challenges is that
we log a ton of data if if a user runs a
search and that search includes data
from you know potentially mult multiple
patients or multiple Concepts or
entities or resources or whatever we're
going to log a whole bunch of stuff in
that moment because if mostly due to
compliance or regulatory requirements
but often because that's what customers
want as well because if if anyone has
ever seen any bit of data they want to
be able to to track that record it and
analyze it and look for anomalies etc
etc etc so we do log a ton primarily for
security and just like access controls
and safety but also I I do think that it
contributes to I mean there's setting
aside the compliance regulatory I'm a
big believer in logging a ton both like
log lines but also Telemetry me like
open Telemetry system Health System
performance dashboards dashboards
dashboards for all that alerting and
that's more of a system health and
system stability perspective but it all
comes together in kind of unified
package yeah I've got a bunch of
questions about logs so one question I
have is how do you avoid logging
sensitive information we treat our logs
as pH so in in healthcare P PR protected
Healthcare information and so the log
data itself it has the exact same
protections and controls as the
production database has and I think this
is relatively common in healthcare you
can have a kind of like a subscriber
relationship to subsets of logs so as a
service provider we can pipe the
relevant logs to our customers as well
and that becomes part of that kind of
handoff agreement about we can either
strip all of the protected information
so rather than showing a person's name
or a lab result it can just be
everything can be distilled down into
just identifiers and Abstract values
like that and if that's what they want
that's what they want it's also possible
to have you know hydrated data as well
and that's more of a question of like
what the use cases for the data yeah I
would imagine the full data is probably
better for developers trying to debug
stuff I mean it's always a trade-off
yeah developers accessing that data is a
long conversation all by itself and I
think that there's a of funny irony when
it comes to data controls and access
that's like I think Google if you think
about the access controls that exist for
something like Gmail famously like high
high high bar for protected data so that
no one can ever access that data it's a
major process to if for some kind of
system stability or bug or an
investigation you do need to get access
to that data there's a long list of
processes and controls you need to go
through to kind of break glass and
investigate there I think that the rest
of the software engineering world would
should aspire to get to that level of
controls and we certainly have an eye
towards that future where everything is
at that level of protection I think it's
really is the gold standard that we
should all be striving for yeah I have
another question around logs how do you
ensure
mutability for like auditing purposes
and things like that so first for our
production databases we are strong
advocates for the like the worm model W
RM right once read many times so most of
our databases are append only and so and
quotequote update operation is really
creating a new version of a resource and
so for any given like the a notion of a
patient or the notion of an appointment
that's really every single change is
being represented as a new version so
you have perfect historical tracking of
of every change and who made that change
and that's in the production database
itself and then as that kind of flows
through the system and ends up in logs
and analytics and data warehouses that's
more of a process question than it is a
strict technical question but everything
is configured to be append only write
only making sure that that data stays
perfectly protected and hygienic like
some of the compliance programs we
talked about earlier in particular
something like sock 2 it comes with a
list of controls and that translates
that into like configurations for
example inside of our Amazon web
services environment there's various AWS
features like cloud trail and I think
it's guard Duty these are AWS features
that you can put various features or
Services into this locked down mode and
if anyone tries to change it or make any
changes to anything it's just going to
set up a whole bunch of alarm Bells it's
going to send emails it's going to send
slack notifications that like hey
someone's in there trying to make a
change to one of these protected
services someone should probably check
this if they had access at all in the
first place okay and then I guess that
would also apply then just to
configuration stuff in general so if you
like have some in your case I think you
guys are doing more like web service
stuff but if you had some sort of device
that you gave to somebody and and it had
some configuration on you would somehow
validate that as well yes like the the
golden bits model of you you've kind of
produced an artifact whether that's a
binary or distributable bit of code and
it's goes through its own validation
like for in our case we have our primary
our web services we have some on-
premise agents for connecting with
Legacy devices that are not cloud
enabled necessarily and same thing there
and I think there's a set of Industry
best practices you produce the binaries
you produce the artifacts you produce
the check sums and publish the test
reports that are associated with those
and just trying to follow best practices
across the board on things like that
great so we mentioned the cloud strike
incident earlier and I saw an
interesting take and I want to get your
thoughts on it and there were a lot of
people saying though they should have
done more manual testing and someone
else pointed out that if you have manual
tests and something falls through the
cracks the solution is end add another
checkbox but how do you verify that that
checkbox actually gets checked and the
work actually gets done versus if it's
automated you update your script once
and then hopefully that should never
happen again because it's now in the
script do you have any thoughts on that
I would tend to agree with the belief
that it should have been an automated
test I I I mean human testing and manual
validation have been with us for a long
time and they will probably be with us
for a long time into the future but I I
think that that's getting pushed further
and further out and as an industry it's
just better if we Embrace more of the
automated testing the automated testing
certainly gets more complicated
especially as you start to think about
the in their case you know that's a huge
number of different devices and network
configurations and deployment
configurations but that's also I guess
part of the job right to make sure that
you're getting your services and your
code into environments that are
representative of the real world as much
as possible so I guess in the medical
and other more highly regulated
Industries you try to control that
Hardware as much as you can if you have
the option I would imagine yeah
absolutely I mean the extreme case here
would be things like devices like a
pacemaker right where you have old
school software Engineers who are
writing code that's like blurs the lines
of application code and operating system
code embedded devices because it needs
to run for a period of years in a
completely automated and offline
environment and that's probably where
some of the most extreme regulations and
testing requirements exist for those
embedded medical devices and then the
Spectrum kind of goes from there great
all right well thank you very much thank
you so much Sam it's great chatting with
you for SC radio this is Sam
tager thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
it e software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at scr.cr
[Music]
team at SE-R doet this and all other
episodes of SC radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening